How to Achieve Emotional Independence
from Parents?
I immigrated to US
when I was 21 along with my brother.
Now, I am 26 years old
and attending college.
I am back for a while
because of some health problem.
I always have hard time
separating from my parents.
Why?
I believe that I have some deep emotional
attachment to my parents.
But now that I am getting older,
I ought to find my own way,
I do earn my spending money
as far as the economic independence,
I would like to get your advice
on how to achieve independence
from my parents emotionally.
I have a very good relationship
with my brother.
I am much attached to my mom
as if we're of one mind and in one body.
I would like to hear your advice
on how to be independent?
Why you want independence
when you are so attached?
(Audience Laughter)
You should live tied together.
But I have to go back now
that a new semester is starting soon.
(Questioner) It is very difficult being
apart and I depend on her a lot.
Then, just quit the school and
live with your mom.
After graduating next year,
if I get a job there,
I would be separated from her.
So, I need to know
how to separate from my parents.
After the age of 20, you need to
be independent from your parents.
(Sunim) How old are you?
(Questioner) 26 years old.
It's too late.
Are you being supported by your parents?
(Questioner) I am living with them now.
Are you getting financial support
from them or not?
(Questioner) Uh...
Are they paying your tuition or not?
(Questioner) Not all of it.
Are you financially independent?
(Questioner) No, but I am receiving
a scholarship from school.
That is your doing.
(Questioner) Not in terms of financial
support,but I want emotional independence.
If you want independence emotionally,
you should just do it.
Where is the technique
to become independent?
If you want to be independent,
be independent.
If you want to be dependent, be dependent.
Why do you have to ask me?
(Questioner) Since I have to leave them
soon, I will feel so.
(Sunim) Feel downhearted?
(Questioner) Yes, a lot
That's very natural.
If I lose this watch that I've had
for a long time, I would miss it or not?
(Questioner) You would.
I would miss it.
It's the same thing.
This is how human minds work.
When we part from something, especially
we like, we feel sad and we miss it.
These are our psychological phenomena.
(Questioner) But I still want
to stay close to them.
That is the reason for suffering.
When you hate someone,
what do you want to do?
You want to be away from that person.
But when you like someone,
you want to be close.
But if you have to be apart
from someone you love,
it is called the suffering of separation.
The pain of parting from someone we love.
Sometimes,
we have to stay with someone we hate.
Why?
Maybe our co-worker, or our spouse.
If we are not in a position
to get a divorce,
we suffer the pain of staying
with someone we hate.
The pain of being with someone we hate.
This is one of our human sufferings.
So, you are experiencing
one of the human sufferings.
This problem is not only with regards
to your mother.
Someday, if you meet a man you love,
but cannot marry him,
you will suffer the same pain.
If you must separate from your brother,
you will feel the same pain.
These things happen all the time.
So, this pain is not caused by
your loving someone.
Our lives entail these separations and
forced stays
regardless of our love or hatred.
There wouldn't be pain
if I get to stay with someone I love,
or if I have to part from someone
I dislike.
What are the other two circumstances?
Parting from someone we love,
or associating with someone we hate.
So we suffer in these circumstances.
These are our great emotional sufferings.
You are now experiencing
one of these situations.
So, accept the fact that you need
to separate even though you love her.
Time will heal this pain.
If I lose this watch,
I will miss it for a couple of days.
But after about 10 days, it will be okay.
It will be okay.
So, what is the best medicine
for a break up pain?
Time is the best medicine.
Likewise, you need to practice
living apart from your mother.
It won't happen overnight.
You will miss your mom
because of your habit of being with her.
This is called inertia.
In physics,
an object in motion will stay in motion.
An object at rest will stay at rest.
For a smoker,
is it hard to quit smoking or not?
It's very difficult.
This is the same thing.
It's not anything special.
The desire to smoke remains
so if you stop smoking, you would suffer.
So, you will suffer because of the habit
of being with her when you're without her.
So, if you have to be apart,
you will be healed naturally after a while
So, don't worry too much.
(Questioner) Yes, thank you.
(Sunim) Yes.
(Audience Applause)
See how overly close relationship between
parents and kids are not necessarily good.
So, you need to cut the emotional ties
during the teenage years. Understand?
You have to start cutting the attachment
during the teen year and
completely sever the emotional ties
when they become adults.
That is how the children
will become independent.
It's the same with death.
Those of you in advanced age,
what do you think?
You may say,
"It'll be good to die in my sleep."
You might say this, right?
You should not die like that.
It's good for the person dying to die
in his sleep,
but for the children left behind,
this causes great suffering. Understand?
So, how should you die?
To cut the emotional attachment,
you should be bedridden for about 3 years.
(Audience Laughter)
If you cause all that misery,
they would say,
"It would be better off dead"
What does that do?
Severs the emotional ties.
If you die like that, would they miss you?
A little but not very much.
It is said that no dutiful children
can outlast long illnesses.
In the old days,
about 3 years of caring for sick parents
can erase the emotional attachments.
These days, the children are so smart
that it only takes about 3 months.
(Audience Laughter)
So, you don't need to be sick
for 3 years.
If you let them change your diapers
for 3 months, the attachment will be gone.
You saw how awful things are
at that woman's home
after 10 years of caring for ill parents.
Then, what is the conflict between
the daughter and the daughter-in-law?
The daughter urges that her mother be
at home rather than in a hospital.
And she doesn't want to have
the artificial respirator removed.
But, what is
the daughter-in-law's position?
It's all talk for the daughter.
But the daughter-in-law is the one
who takes care of her at home.
She is not even her own mother
and she is not that attached
to her mother-in-law.
The mother-in-law was just a part of
the package when she got married.
So, the daughter-in-law wants to leave
the mother-in-law at the hospital.
It's very hard for the daughter-in-law
if this situation is prolonged too long.
The daughter will feel the same way
if she were the daughter-in-law.
It would be good if the daughter-in-law
can empathize with the daughter,
and the daughter can empathize
with the daughter-in-law.
But, we humans do not operate like this.
We only think about
our own self-interest.
So, this sort of problem
will be easier to resolve
if we can understand
the other's positions.
So, those of you who are advanced in age,
stop wishing to die in your sleep.
You should be ill for at least a year
before you die.
Who is that for?
For your children.
This helps sever their attachment to you.
If you don't want your children to cry
and suffer after you're gone,
you need to burden them
before you die.
Then, they would say,
'Good bye" and cut the ties.
Otherwise, they would keep crying.
If you had souls, would you be able to
leave them when they're suffering so much?
You couldn't leave.
Then you'd become a wandering spirits.
If you did die in your sleep, is it bad?
No. It's good for you
but you leave your children suffering.
Understand?
So, dying in your sleep is fine and
being sick for a while is fine, too.
Dying in sleep is good for you but being
sick awhile is good for the children.
No need to feel bad.
Don't worry about
the children's difficulties.
"You need to go through this
so that you can detach from me easily."
"I am suffering in illness so that
you could have less pain afterwards."
(Audience Laughter)
And just let things be.
You ought to sever the emotional ties
like this.
We think that it's good to be
emotionally close.
But it isn't always so.
People who are stuck like glue
need to detach themselves from each other.
Parents say,
"I don't want anything from you."
"I am doing everything for your sake."
"I tell you to study for your sake,
I nag for your own good."
These are what the parents say.
But the children are hassled to death
by their parents.
So, this is not the right attitude.
This can be counter-productive.
And don't compare with other families.
Don't be envious of couples
who are very close.
If one dies in such case,
the other cannot go on living.
Understand?
Is it true or not?
It's true.
Make some trouble before you die,
so she can detach easily afterwards.
So that she can remarry someone else
later.
If you are too close, after one dies,
the other would be lost, first.
Second,
she/he won't be able to live alone.
Third, she/he can't meet another person.
Why?
No one can measure up to the late spouse.
Nobody is good enough.
So, the dead person defeats
the living person.
Then, she/he will have to live
a lonely life clinging to the dead spouse.
So, no need to be so envious
of overly close couple.
Got it?
If your spouse is average,
it's good that he is.
If your spouse is annoying,
it's good that she is.
A woman with an overly attentive husband
doesn't even know how to drive.
You know?
But if your husband doesn't drive you
or put gas in the car,
you have to pump your own gas and
you have to drive yourself.
You'll be more capable.
This is much better.
But you get so envious of others.
That's not necessary.
This is not to say that
an attentive husband is bad.
They are all fine.
Either the attentive husbands
or the inattentive ones.
There aren't too many healthy women
whose husbands are overly attentive.
They live like children
who can't do things for themselves.
We don't even know
what is truly good for us.
That is why we say that
life goes up and down.
We don't need to agonize over things
that don't go our way.
Growing up in a difficult home life
is not necessarily a bad thing.
It could make you be more independent
and more self-reliant.